		<Document type="Biological_full_article">
			<DocID type="BMC_ID">1471-2105-8-225</DocID>
				<DocumentPart type="Title">
					<sentence id="S1.1">Mining prokaryotic genomes for unknown amino acids: a stop-codon-based approach</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.2">Abstract</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SubSectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.3">Background</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.4">Selenocysteine and pyrrolysine are the 21st and 22nd amino acids, which are genetically encoded by stop codons.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.5">Since a number of microbial genomes have been completely sequenced to date, it is tempting to ask <xcope id="X1.5.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.5.1">whether</cue> the 23rd amino acid is left undiscovered in these genomes</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.6">Recently, a computational study addressed this question and reported that <xcope id="X1.6.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.6.1">no</cue> tRNA gene for unknown amino acid was found in genome sequences available</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.7">However, <xcope id="X1.7.2">performance of the tRNA prediction program on an unknown tRNA family, which <xcope id="X1.7.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.7.1">may</cue> have atypical sequence and structure</xcope>, is <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.7.2">unclear</cue></xcope>, thereby rendering their result inconclusive.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.8">A protein-level study will provide independent insight into the novel amino acid.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SubSectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.9">Results</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.10"><xcope id="X1.10.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.10.1">Assuming</cue> that the 23rd amino acid is also encoded by a stop codon</xcope>, we systematically predicted proteins that contain stop-codon-encoded amino acids from 191 prokaryotic genomes.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.11">Since our prediction method relies only on the conservation patterns of primary sequences, it also provides an opportunity to search novel selenoproteins and other readthrough proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.12">It successfully recovered many of currently known selenoproteins and pyrrolysine proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.13">However, <xcope id="X1.13.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.13.1">no</cue> promising candidate for the 23rd amino acid was detected</xcope>, and only one novel selenoprotein was predicted.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SubSectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.14">Conclusion</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.15">Our result <xcope id="X1.15.3"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.15.3">suggests</cue> that <xcope id="X1.15.2">the unknown amino acid encoded by stop codons does <xcope id="X1.15.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.15.1">not</cue> exist</xcope>, <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.15.2">or</cue> its phylogenetic distribution is rather limited</xcope></xcope>, which is in agreement with the previous study on tRNA.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.16">The method described here can be used in future studies to explore novel readthrough events from complete genomes, which are rapidly growing.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Title">
					<sentence id="S1.17">Background</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.18">Stop codon readthrough is a phenomenon in which the translation process does <xcope id="X1.18.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.18.1">not</cue> terminate at a stop codon</xcope>, and an amino acid is inserted there instead 12.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.19">In some cases, the inserted amino acid is <xcope id="X1.19.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.19.1">not</cue> one of the 20 amino acids</xcope> but a noncanonical one.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.20">Two such amino acids have been discovered to date: selenocysteine 34 and pyrrolysine 56.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.21">Because each of them have specialized tRNA genes for decoding and can be considered extensions of the standard genetic code, they are called the 21st and 22nd amino acids, respectively.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.22">Selenocysteine, the 21st amino acid, is encoded by stop codon UGA, and organisms that use selenocysteine have been found from all three domains of life.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.23">Its insertion into UGA is directed by SECIS (selenocysteine insertion sequence) elements, a stem-loop structure on the selenoprotein mRNA.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.24">Along with the progress of genome sequencing projects, computational prediction methods of selenocysteine-containing proteins (selenoproteins) have been developed by several research groups 78910, and the repertoire of selenoproteins has been greatly expanded 1112.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.25">Pyrrolysine, the 22nd amino acid encoded by stop codon UAG, was recently discovered from a methanogenic archaea 56.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.26">Currently, only methanogenic archaea of the order Methanosarcinales and one bacterium are considered to utilize pyrrolysine 13.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.27">The limited phylogenetic distribution of pyrrolysine <xcope id="X1.27.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.27.2">suggests</cue> that its incorporation into the genetic code of methanogen is relatively recent, and the insertion mechanism of a novel amino acid <xcope id="X1.27.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.27.1">can</cue> evolve in a shorter period of time than anticipated</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.28">This <xcope id="X1.28.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.28.1">raises an interesting question</cue>:: ""Is there a 23rd amino acid"</xcope>?".</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.29">If such an amino acid is discovered, it will deepen our understanding of the evolution and diversity of the genetic code.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.30">Because genome sequences of various prokaryotes are available today, there will be a chance to discover the novel amino acid via analysis of these genomes.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.31">Since both the 21st and 22nd amino acids are encoded by stop codons, the prime suspect is other stop codons (e.g. stop codon UAA), although the possibility of sense codons certainly remains.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.32">Using this clue, computational screening methods of the 23rd amino acid can be designed.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.33">Recently, Lobanov et al. addressed this problem by searching tRNAs with anticodons corresponding to stop codons 14.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.34">They analyzed 146 prokaryotic genomes, but <xcope id="X1.34.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.34.1">no</cue> likely tRNA of the novel amino acid was detected</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.35">They concluded that the 23rd amino acid <xcope id="X1.35.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.35.1">would</cue> have a limited phylogenetic distribution, if it exists</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.36">However, programs for tRNA identification are based on the features of known tRNAs and do not necessarily perform well on unknown ones.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.37">Actually, tRNASec and tRNAPyl have unusual secondary structures 515 and often escape detection by programs <xcope id="X1.37.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.37.1">without</cue> special consideration</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.38">Lobanov et al. thus developed a sensitive search method to deal with this problem, but they also admitted that it <xcope id="X1.38.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.38.2">would</cue> <xcope id="X1.38.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.38.1">fail</cue> to identify highly unusual tRNAs</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.39">There is another approach to searching for the 23rd amino acid.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.40">By enumerating ORFs that have an inframe stop codon from genomes and examining their evolutionary conservation, candidate proteins can be predicted.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.41">Because such an ORF-based study is independent from the tRNA analysis, it can <xcope id="X1.41.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.41.1">either</cue> identify candidate organisms missed by the previous study <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.41.1">or</cue> strengthen its negative conclusion</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.42">Here we report a comprehensive analysis of prokaryotic ORFs that contain an inframe stop codon.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.43">Through enumeration of theoretical ORFs and inspection of their evolutionary conservation, candidates of readthrough proteins were predicted.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.44">They contained many of the known proteins with stop-codon-encoded amino acids, but almost no novel candidates were identified.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.45">Therefore, <xcope id="X1.45.1">the unknown amino acid, if it is encoded by a stop codon, is <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.45.1">unlikely</cue> to exist in the current databases of microbial genomes</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.46">The consequences for selenoproteins and other readthrough genes are also discussed.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Title">
					<sentence id="S1.47">Results</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.48">Basic ideas</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.49">In this study, we focus on theoretical ORFs with one inframe stop codon, termed "interrupted ORFs" (iORFs) (Figure 1a).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.50">If we enumerate all iORFs from microbial genomes, most of the readthrough genes will be included in them.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.51">However, the vast majority of the enumerated iORFs will be biologically meaningless.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.52">To filter out such meaningless iORFs, we required the iORFs to have at least one homolog in other genomes, because evolutionary conservation of primary sequence is a strong indicator of functional importance.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.53">However, this condition is <xcope id="X1.53.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.53.1">not</cue> sufficient</xcope>, since two major problems remain:: pseudogenes and two adjacent genes.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.54">The first problem is that even if an iORF has homologs in other species, it <xcope id="X1.54.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.54.2">could</cue> be <xcope id="X1.54.1">a pseudogene <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.54.1">or</cue> a product of sequencing error</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.55">The second problem is that adjacent genes on the same reading frame <xcope id="X1.55.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.55.1">may</cue> satisfy the condition of conserved iORFs</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.56">In particular, gene pairs within an operon are problematic because their gene arrangement is often conserved.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.57">If <xcope id="X1.57.2">the intergenic distance between two genes in an operon <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.57.2">happens</cue> to be a multiple of three</xcope>, they <xcope id="X1.57.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.57.1">look like</cue> a conserved readthrough gene</xcope>.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="FigureLegend">
					<sentence id="S1.58">Basic ideas of the prediction method</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.59">Basic ideas of the prediction method.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.60">(a) Schematic illustration of an interrupted ORF (iORF).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.61">(b) Readthrough genes can be distinguished from two adjacent genes based on the results of BLAST searches.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.62">Boxes denote iORFs, and &#215; indicates the inframe stop codon.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.63">Shaded regions represent actual protein-coding regions.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.64">If an iORF codes a readthrough protein, BLAST hits from other organisms will cover the inframe stop codon.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.65">In contrast, if the iORF consists of two adjacent genes, many hits that do <xcope id="X1.65.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.65.1">not</cue> cover the inframe stop codon</xcope> will be found.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.66">To discriminate them from true readthrough genes, evolutionary information was exploited.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.67">In order to eliminate pseudogenes and sequencing errors, conservation of iORFs and their inframe stop codons was examined.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.68">Since pseudogenes are less conserved, and sequencing errors are relatively rare events, they will <xcope id="X1.68.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.68.1">not</cue> have homologous iORFs in other species</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.69">Even if they do, the position or type (UAA, UAG or UGA) of their inframe stop codons will <xcope id="X1.69.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.69.1">not</cue> coincide</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.70">In this way, they can be eliminated as candidates.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.71">A drawback of this criterion is that it limits the target of our study to readthrough genes conserved across two or more species.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.72">In other words, species-specific readthrough genes are <xcope id="X1.72.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.72.1">not</cue> in the scope of this study</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.73">To address the second problem, adjacent gene pairs were filtered out by examining boundaries of sequence alignments between iORFs and its homologs (Figure 1b).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.74">The stop-codon-encoded amino acids of prokaryotes are usually located inside domains, the units of evolutionary sequence conservation.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.75">Therefore, the aligned regions of readthrough proteins contain their inframe stop codon.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.76">Based on this observation, each iORF was required to have:: (i) at least one homolog from other organisms that covers the inframe stop codon and (ii) <xcope id="X1.76.2"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.76.2">no</cue> homolog that does <xcope id="X1.76.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.76.1">not</cue> cover the stop codon</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.77">Note that, however, if the whole length of an iORF was used as a query sequence, this procedure will erroneously discard multidomain readthrough proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.78">To avoid this problem, a partial sequence around the inframe stop codon was used as a query.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.79">Prediction procedure</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.80">The prediction schema is shown in Figure 2.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.81">A total of 191 prokaryotes were analyzed in this study, of which 166 are bacteria and 25 are archaea.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.82">They were selected from 328 prokaryotes with completely sequenced genomes by excluding closely related species.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.83">From the genome sequences of the 191 organisms, all possible iORFs were enumerated.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.84">Two conditions were imposed on the geometry of the iORFs (Figure 1a).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.85">First, only iORFs longer than 80 codons were extracted.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.86">Secondly, margins between the inframe stop codon and both termini of the iORF must be longer than 10 codons.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.87">The total number of iORFs extracted under these conditions was 2,969,958.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.88">Next, iORFs that overlap RNA genes or protein-coding genes in different reading frames were discarded.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.89">This test significantly reduced the number of iORFs to 390,926.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="FigureLegend">
					<sentence id="S1.90">A flowchart of the prediction procedure</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.91">A flowchart of the prediction procedure.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.92">Several steps are omitted for simplicity.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.93">Detailed explanation is given in the text.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.94">As noted above, the target of this study is evolutionarily conserved iORFs.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.95">Thus, it was examined <xcope id="X1.95.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.95.1">whether</cue> the iORFs have homologous regions in other genomes</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.96">The 390,926 iORFs were translated into amino acid sequences and subjected to TBLASTN 16 against the 191 genome sequences.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.97"><xcope id="X1.97.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.97.1">Instead of</cue> the whole length of the amino acid sequence</xcope>, a window of 101 residues centered at the inframe stop codon was used as a BLAST query.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.98">After the BLAST searches, iORFs that have at least one interspecific hit that contains the inframe stop codon were collected.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.99"><xcope id="X1.99.3"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.99.3">Whether</cue> the codon aligned to the inframe stop codon is <xcope id="X1.99.2">a nonsense codon <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.99.2">or</cue> <xcope id="X1.99.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.99.1">not</cue></xcope></xcope></xcope> was neglected at this stage.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.100">There were 94,690 iORFs that have interspecific hits.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.101">The result of the above homology searches was also used for the boundary analysis (Figure 1b).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.102">An iORF was discarded if there were any BLAST hits that do <xcope id="X1.102.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.102.1">not</cue> cover the inframe stop codon</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.103">A total of 26,003 iORF satisfied the above criteria.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.104">To examine intrafamily conservation of the inframe stop codons, these iORFs were clustered into protein families based on sequence similarity.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.105">After removal of singletons, 679 clusters with two or more members were obtained.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.106">A cluster was discarded unless all members of the cluster had the same type of inframe stop codons (UAA, UAG or UGA).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.107">The locations of the inframe stop codons were also required to be identical in the multiple sequence alignment of the cluster members.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.108">These conditions reduced the number of clusters to 273.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.109">Manual inspection of these 273 clusters revealed that they still contain many false positives that are unrelated to stop-codon-encoded amino acids.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.110">Hence, three-step filtering procedures were applied to remove the false positives.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.111">Briefly, the first filter assesses protein-likeliness based on the signal of purifying selection, while the second and third filters try to remove adjacent gene pairs using the pattern of BLAST alignments (for details, see Materials and Methods).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.112">As a result of the filtering, the number of candidate clusters was reduced to 32.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.113">Through manual inspection of the BLAST alignments, 11 clusters were discarded because <xcope id="X1.113.1">they are highly <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.113.1">unlikely</cue> to code readthrough proteins</xcope>.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.114">Known proteins in the predicted clusters</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.115">The clusters predicted by our method are summarized in Table 1.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.116">Of the 21 clusters, 15 were known selenoproteins, and four were known pyrrolysine proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.117">To assess the sensitivity of our method, the result was compared with a list of prokaryotic selenoproteins reported by Kryukov and Gladyshev 12.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.118">Since our target is readthrough genes conserved across two or more species, such selenoprotein families were selected from their list.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.119">There were 15 families satisfying this criterion, but one family, proline reductase, was excluded because it was found in only one organism in our dataset.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.120">Of the 14 families, 11 were found in our prediction result.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.121">The three families we <xcope id="X1.121.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.121.1">failed</cue> to find</xcope> were SelW-like protein, peroxiredoxin and thiol:protein disulphide oxidoreductase.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.122">SelW-like protein was below the threshold of detection, because its stop codon is near the N-terminus and the amino acid sequences of its members are too divergent.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.123">The reason why <xcope id="X1.123.1">the two other families were <cue type="negation" ref="X1.123.1">not</cue> detected</xcope> is more complex.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.124">Since these two families are homologous, they were grouped into an identical cluster at the clustering stage of our method.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.125">However, the positions of selenocysteine were different between the two families (Figure 3).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.126">The cluster was thus discarded because of an <xcope id="X1.126.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.126.2">apparent</cue> <xcope id="X1.126.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.126.1">lack</cue> of stop codon conservation</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.127">To deal with a situation like this, a reexamination of the clustering threshold and subdivision of clusters will be required.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="TableLegend">
					<sentence id="S1.128">Predicted clusters of readthrough proteins</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.129">A plus sign in a locus <xcope id="X1.129.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.129.2">indicates that</cue> the genomic coordinates of the iORF can be described by a concatenation of two <xcope id="X1.129.1">genes <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.129.1">or</cue> regions</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.130">For example, "GSU2293 + downstream" means that the iORF consists of the gene GSU2293 and its downstream sequence.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.131"><xcope id="X1.131.1">HesB family was <cue type="negation" ref="X1.131.1">not</cue> clustered into one family</xcope>, because their sequences were too short and diverged.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="FigureLegend">
					<sentence id="S1.132"><xcope id="X1.132.1">Selenoprotein families we <cue type="negation" ref="X1.132.1">failed</cue> to detect</xcope> because of nonconserved location of stop codons</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.133"><xcope id="X1.133.1">Selenoprotein families we <cue type="negation" ref="X1.133.1">failed</cue> to detect</xcope> because of nonconserved location of stop codons.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.134">Selenocysteine residues of Peroxiredoxin-like protein families constitute homologous redox motifs (TXXU and UXXC), but their positions are different between two families.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.135">Columns are colored according to sequence conservation.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.136">Selenocysteine residues are shown in red, and the other residues in the redox motifs are shown in yellow.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.137">Prx; Peroxiredoxin, TPO; thiol:protein disulphide oxidereductase, Adeh; Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans, Gmet; Geobacter metallireducens, Gsul; G. sulfurreducens, Dpsy; Desulfotalea psychrophila.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.138">The alignments were computed using ClustalW, and the figures were generated using Jalview.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.139">Of the four pyrrolysine proteins detected, three methylamine methyltransferases have been experimentally confirmed to contain pyrrolysine 617.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.140">The rest is a cluster of TetR-like transcriptional regulators from Methanosarcina acetivorans and M. barkeri.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.141">Since the genome annotation of M. acetivorans describes this protein as a gene containing an inframe amber codon, we classified it as a ''known'' candidate, although it is still <xcope id="X1.141.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.141.2">unclear</cue> <xcope id="X1.141.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.141.1">whether</cue> it really contains pyrrolysine</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.142">The genome annotation of M. acetivorans also includes several amber-containing genes <xcope id="X1.142.1">that were <cue type="negation" ref="X1.142.1">absent</cue> from our prediction result</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.143">They are a methlycobamide:CoM methylase and four transposases 18.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.144">The reason why <xcope id="X1.144.1">they were <cue type="negation" ref="X1.144.1">not</cue> detected</xcope> is that only one species in our dataset had an amber-containing form of these proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.145">This is unavoidable because of the inability of our method to detect species-specific readthrough events.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.146">It is the price for reliably excluding pseudogenes and sequencing errors.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.147">Unknown candidates in the predicted clusters</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.148">The successful detection of many known proteins is encouraging, because our method relies only on general properties of proteins that contain stop-codon-encoded amino acids, but <xcope id="X1.148.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.148.1">not</cue> on specific features of selenocysteine or pyrrolysine</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.149">Therefore, unknown clusters in our candidates have possibilities for the 23rd amino acid or novel readthrough proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.150">There were two such clusters (Table 1).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.151">The first cluster is comprised of c-type cytochromes from &#948;-proteobacteria Geobacter sulfurreducens and G. metallireducens.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.152">The N-terminal part of the sequence contains five CXXCH heme-biding motifs, while the C-terminal part has <xcope id="X1.152.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.152.1">no</cue> similarity with any characterized proteins</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.153">Homology search against unfinished microbial genomes identified seven homologous proteins from four other &#948;-proteobacteria species.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.154">Multiple sequence alignment of these sequences is shown in Figure 4a.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.155">Multiple sequence alignments of novel candidate proteins</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.156">Multiple sequence alignments of novel candidate proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.157">(a) A selenoprotein candidate from Geobacter sulfurreducens and its homologs.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.158">The <xcope id="X1.158.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.158.2">possible</cue> selenocysteine residues</xcope> are shown in red, and <xcope id="X1.158.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.158.1">putative</cue> heme-binding motifs</xcope> are underlined.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.159">Note that sequence conservation near the selenocysteine is comparable to that of the N-terminal cytochrome domain.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.160">A protein Dpro_2 contains yet another inframe stop codon (TAG) at the column 189.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.161">It will be <xcope id="X1.161.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.161.1">either</cue> a sequencing error <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.161.1">or</cue> a pseudogene</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.162">Gsul; G. sulfurreducens, Gmet; G. metallireducens, Gura; G. uraniumreducens, Gfrc; Geobacter sp. FRC-32, Dace; Desulfuromonas acetoxidans, Dpro; Delta proteobacterium MLMS-1.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.163">(b) Hypothetical proteins from Geobacter species.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.164">The inframe stop codons (TAG) are shown in red.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.165">This cluster is <xcope id="X1.165.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.165.1">probably</cue> an artifact of close phylogenetic relationship</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.166">We <xcope id="X1.166.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.166.2">expect</cue> that this cluster <xcope id="X1.166.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.166.1">may</cue> represent a novel selenoprotein family</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.167">This is because the inframe stop codons of these proteins are exclusively TGA, and all of the above organisms possess selenocysteine insertion machinery <xcope id="X1.167.1">(data <cue type="negation" ref="X1.167.1">not</cue> shown)</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.168">High conservation of residues near the inframe stop codon also <xcope id="X1.168.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.168.1">suggests</cue> the importance of this region</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.169">If they are true selenoproteins, this protein family becomes a rare instance of selenoprotein that <xcope id="X1.169.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.169.1">lacks</cue> non-selenocysteine homologs</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.170">However, computational analysis of sequences immediately downstream of the inframe stop codons <xcope id="X1.170.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.170.1">failed</cue> to identify SECIS elements</xcope>, which is a hallmark of selenocysteine-containing genes.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.171">Therefore, yet another <xcope id="X1.171.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.171.1">possibility</cue> is that they are a highly conserved operon</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.172">An experimental verification is necessary to distinguish these two possibilities.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.173">The second cluster consists of two hypothetical proteins, again from G. sulfurreducens and G. metallireducens (Figure 4b).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.174">In contrast to the first cluster, <xcope id="X1.174.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.174.1">no</cue> homolog was identified from other species</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.175">This cluster is <xcope id="X1.175.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.175.2">probably</cue> a false positive and <xcope id="X1.175.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.175.1">not</cue> readthrough proteins</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.176">This is because the residues near the inframe stop codons are poorly conserved.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.177">Moreover, the C-terminal extensions are quite short (about 20 aa).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.178">The sequence conservation in this region can be easily explained by the close phylogenetic relationship between the two species.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.179">In summary, although a possible selenoprotein was newly identified, there was <xcope id="X1.179.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.179.1">no</cue> promising candidate for an unknown amino acid encoded by a stop codon</xcope>.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.180">Stop codon usage in the pre-filtering clusters</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.181"><xcope id="X1.181.1">The above negative result <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.181.1">could</cue> be explained if the filtering process, which is the final step of the prediction method (Figure 2), was too strict</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.182">Although the raw output of the search for evolutionarily conserved iORFs was 273 clusters, most of them were discarded at the subsequent filtering stage.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.183">Because we have <xcope id="X1.183.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.183.1">no</cue> a priori knowledge about the 23rd amino acid</xcope>, cutoff thresholds for the filtering procedures were determined based on the known readthrough proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.184">This is practically indispensable for objective classification of candidates, but there is <xcope id="X1.184.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.184.1">no guarantee</cue> that unknown proteins with the 23rd amino acid will score higher than the thresholds</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.185">To explore <xcope id="X1.185.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.185.1">whether</cue> a number of good candidates lie below the thresholds</xcope>, the 273 clusters were analyzed in a way independent from filtering.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.186">If an organism has many readthrough proteins, proteins from the organism will frequently appear in the 273 clusters.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.187">Moreover, relative usage of the inframe stop codons will deviate from that of usual termination signals in the proteome.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.188">Figure 5 shows the discrepancies between relative usage of the inframe and C-terminal stop codons of 127 organisms in the pre-filtering clusters.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.189">Only seven organisms had statistically significant discrepancies (P &lt; 0.05), and all of them are known to utilize selenocysteine or pyrrolysine.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="FigureLegend">
					<sentence id="S1.190">Discrepancies of stop codon usages between the inframe and C-terminal stop codons</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.191">Discrepancies of stop codon usages between the inframe and C-terminal stop codons.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.192">The inframe stop codon usage is taken from the pre-filtering clusters, and the C-terminal usage is computed based on the annotated proteins of the organism.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.193">Red circle: an organism with pyrrolysine, blue; selenocysteine, yellow; both pyrrolysine and selenocysteine, white; <xcope id="X1.193.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.193.1">neither</cue> pyrrolysine <cue type="negation" ref="X1.193.1">nor</cue> selenocysteine</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.194">The organisms are ordered by their discrepancy scores.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.195">The discrepancy score is the negative logarithm of a p-value of Fisher's exact test.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.196">The dotted line indicates significance level 0.05 after a correction for multiple testing.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.197">When top ten organisms were examined, only Gluconobacter oxydans was an organism <xcope id="X1.197.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.197.1">not</cue> known to have stop-codon-encoded amino acids</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.198">An inspection of the G. oxydans iORFs in the 273 clusters revealed that their inframe stop codons are dominated by TAA, but all of them belong to a single protein cluster associated with transposable elements.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.199">Because it <xcope id="X1.199.4"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.199.4">seems</cue> <xcope id="X1.199.3"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.199.3">unlikely</cue> that an insertion system of novel amino acid evolves solely for transposable elements</xcope></xcope>, <xcope id="X1.199.1"><xcope id="X1.199.2">this organism <cue type="negation" ref="X1.199.1">cannot</cue> be <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.199.2">considered</cue> as a good candidate of the 23rd amino acid</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.200">Sensitivity of this test is not high because many organisms that utilize selenocysteine were below the defined threshold.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.201">However, the result agrees with the filtering-dependent analysis that <xcope id="X1.201.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.201.1">no</cue> candidate of the novel stop-codon-encoded amino acid is detectable in the current dataset</xcope>.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Title">
					<sentence id="S1.202">Discussion</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.203">As the number of completely sequenced genomes increases, several research groups started to predict proteins that contain stop-codon-encoded amino acids through computational analyses.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.204">Most of them are aimed at identification of selenoproteins, reflecting concerns from the scientific community and accumulated knowledge on selenocysteine.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.205">In order to improve prediction specificity, they have fully exploited the known features of selenocysteine, such as the SECIS elements or cysteine homologs, which have cysteine in place of selenocysteine.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.206">However, since the target of this study is the 23rd amino acid, and there is <xcope id="X1.206.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.206.1">no</cue> a priori knowledge</xcope>, only general properties of stop-codon-encoded amino acids can be used for prediction.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.207">Such general-purpose algorithms have also been developed to date.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.208">The method of Chaudhuri and Yeates 10 extracts iORFs from microbial genomes and analyzes sequence conservation around the inframe stop codon.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.209">Their method is thus similar to ours and applicable to both selenocysteine and pyrrolysine.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.210">Perrodou et al. 19 constructed a database of predicted recoding events in microbes.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.211">Their method is applicable not only to stop codon readthrough but also to frameshift.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.212">However, both of them did <xcope id="X1.212.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.212.1">not</cue> apply their methods to search for novel amino acids</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.213">Therefore, <xcope id="X1.213.1">the question of the 23rd amino acid has <cue type="negation" ref="X1.213.1">not</cue> been investigated from the viewpoint of coding sequences</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.214">Additionally, the previous methods <xcope id="X1.214.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.214.1">cannot</cue> effectively discriminate pseudogenes from readthrough genes</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.215">For instance, Chaudhuri and Yeates reported a homolog of cobalamin biosynthesis protein CobN as a novel candidate of pyrrolysine protein.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.216">However, the gene is <xcope id="X1.216.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.216.2">probably</cue> a pseudogene</xcope> because it contains an inframe TAA codon in addition to the TAG codon, and only <xcope id="X1.216.1">one species <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.216.1">seems</cue> to have the amber-containing form of the gene</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.217">The previous methods also <xcope id="X1.217.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.217.2">assume</cue> that proteins with stop-codon-encoded amino acids will have non-readthrough homologs (i.e., homologous proteins that do <xcope id="X1.217.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.217.1">not</cue> have inframe stop codons)</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.218">However, that is not necessarily true.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.219">For example, pyrrolysine-containing monomethylamine methyltransferases adopt TIM barrel fold 6, but their primary sequences do <xcope id="X1.219.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.219.1">not</cue> exhibit detectable similarity to other TIM barrel proteins</xcope> because of evolutionary divergence.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.220">Dimethylamine methyltransferases also <xcope id="X1.220.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.220.1">lack</cue> non-readthrough homologs</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.221">Yet another example is glycine reductase selenoprotein A.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.222">Only the selenocysteine-containing form of the enzyme is currently known 20.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.223">Therefore, it is important <xcope id="X1.223.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.223.1">not</cue> to assume non-readthrough homologs for exploring novel candidates</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.224">If any non-readthrough homologs are registered in public sequence databases, a careful annotation process of a newly sequenced genome will be able to detect readthrough genes, even though <xcope id="X1.224.1">they <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.224.1">may</cue> be annotated as pseudogenes</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.225">However, if all members of a gene family have stop codon readthrough, correct annotation of their gene structure will be extremely difficult, and all of them will be split into two distinct genes.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.226">The method reported here is unique in that it does <xcope id="X1.226.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.226.1">not</cue> assume non-readthrough homologs</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.227">Using this method, a systematic screening of the 23rd amino acid and other readthrough genes was carried out.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.228">Many of the currently known selenoproteins and pyrrolysine proteins were recovered, indicating the effectiveness of this approach.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.229">In particular, successful detection of pyrrolysine-containing methyltransferases and selenoprotein A should be noted.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.230">However, almost no novel candidates for readthrough genes were predicted.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.231">What can be concluded from this result?</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.232">The most <xcope id="X1.232.3"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.232.3">likely</cue> explanation</xcope> is that <xcope id="X1.232.2">the 23rd amino acid does <xcope id="X1.232.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.232.1">not</cue> exist</xcope>, <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.232.2">or</cue> its distribution on the tree of life is rather limited</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.233">Although a broad spectrum of taxonomic groups has been subjected to genome sequencing, the genomes of most microbial species on the earth have yet to be determined.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.234"><xcope id="X1.234.1">The unknown amino acid <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.234.1">may</cue> be used by these species</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.235">Alternatively, only one organism in our dataset <xcope id="X1.235.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.235.1">may</cue> have the 23rd amino acid</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.236">This is because our method is limited to readthrough genes conserved across two or more species.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.237">If the novel amino acid appears in younger, non-conserved sequences, our technique will miss them.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.238">In either case, the distribution of the 23rd amino acid will be significantly narrower than that of selenocysteine, which has scattered but wide distribution 21.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.239">This conclusion coincides with and strengthens that of the previous research on tRNA 14.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.240">Yet another <xcope id="X1.240.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.240.2">possibility</cue> is that the 23rd amino acid exists but is <xcope id="X1.240.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.240.1">not</cue> encoded by stop codons</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.241">It is well known that the genetic code varies in several organisms 22.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.242">Thus, certain organisms <xcope id="X1.242.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.242.1">may</cue> use one of the sense codons for the novel amino acid</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.243">Because codons for most amino acids are degenerate, redefinition of <xcope id="X1.243.1">one of them is <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.243.1">feasible</cue></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.244">However, that possibility is beyond the scope of this study and is left as an open problem.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.245">Bioinformatics analysis of unusual tRNA genes and codon usage <xcope id="X1.245.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.245.1">may</cue> provide insights into this problem</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.246">In addition to the 23rd amino acid, our method can simultaneously explore selenoproteins and other readthrough proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.247">A common <xcope id="X1.247.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.247.1">assumption</cue> in microbial selenoprotein predictions is that selenoproteins will have cysteine homologs</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.248">Zhang et al. 20 examined the validity of this assumption using a SECIS-based method and concluded that selenoproteins <xcope id="X1.248.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.248.1">without</cue> cysteine homologs</xcope> will be extremely rare.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.249">Our method can reassess this assumption in a SECIS-independent way.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.250">Such selenoproteins identified through our screening of nearly 200 microbial genomes were selenoprotein A and only one uncertain candidate.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.251">Therefore, selenoproteins that <xcope id="X1.251.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.251.1">lack</cue> cysteine homologs</xcope> will be scarce, as previously reported.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.252">Other readthrough proteins with canonical amino acids (i.e., proteins that have canonical amino acids at their inframe stop codons) are quite rare in prokaryotes 1.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.253">The result reported here is in agreement, but it is <xcope id="X1.253.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.253.1">not</cue> conclusive</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.254">This is because our method <xcope id="X1.254.3"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.254.3">assumes</cue> that stop-codon-encoded amino acid is located inside a domain</xcope>, but it is <xcope id="X1.254.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.254.2">unclear</cue> <xcope id="X1.254.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.254.1">whether</cue> it holds true in prokaryotic readthrough with canonical amino acids</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.255">At least, only one experimentally-confirmed example from a pathogenic strain of Escherichia coli 23, <xcope id="X1.255.2">whose genome is <cue type="negation" ref="X1.255.2">not</cue> yet determined</xcope>, does <xcope id="X1.255.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.255.1">not</cue> obey this rule</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.256">What can be concluded from our result is that this type of readthrough will be located outside of domains, such as a linker between two domains.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.257">Such a stop codon <xcope id="X1.257.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.257.1">may</cue> behave as a switch that regulates production of short and long isoforms from a single mRNA, as in readthrough genes from viruses</xcope> 24.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Title">
					<sentence id="S1.258">Conclusion</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.259">To explore the possibility of a 23rd amino acid, ORFs in prokaryotic genomes were investigated in a comprehensive way.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.260">Although many of the currently known selenoproteins and pyrrolysine proteins were successfully detected, <xcope id="X1.260.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.260.1">no</cue> candidate for the 23rd amino acid was discovered</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.261">Therefore, if such an amino acid exists, it will have limited distribution in the tree of life.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.262">Alternatively, <xcope id="X1.262.1">it <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.262.1">may</cue> be encoded by one of the sense codons</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.263">From the viewpoint of selenoprotein prediction, the sensitivity of our method was lower than an existing method.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.264">However, our method has several unique features.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.265">It is applicable to general readthrough genes and rigorously excludes pseudogenes and sequencing errors.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.266">Moreover, it does <xcope id="X1.266.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.266.1">not</cue> assume the occurrence of non-readthrough homologs in the public databases</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.267">It will help in identification of novel readthrough genes from the rapidly expanding collection of complete microbial genomes.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Title">
					<sentence id="S1.268">Methods</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.269">Enumeration of iORFs from prokaryotic genomes</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.270">A total of 328 complete genome sequences of prokaryotes were downloaded from the KEGG FTP site 25 in April 2006.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.271">From them, 191 representative organisms were selected by excluding close relatives.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.272">The threshold was set to average sequence identity 90% of two house-keeping genes, DNA polymerase III &#945; subunit and alanyl-tRNA synthetase.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.273">From these 191 genomes, iORFs longer than 80 codons were enumerated using inhouse software, which is available from the author's web site 26.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.274">Both upstream and downstream regions of its inframe stop codon were required to be longer than 10 codons.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.275">Two stop codons of an iORF (i.e. the inframe and C-terminal stops) can be any combination of canonical stop codons (TAA, TAG, TGA).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.276">However, for Mycoplasma, only TAA and TAG were used.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.277">Three codons ATG, TTG and GTG were allowed to be start signals.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.278">The iORFs of each organism were compared with protein-coding genes of the organism using BLASTX.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.279">If an iORF matched any protein-coding genes (E-value &lt; 10-3) and their reading frames did <xcope id="X1.279.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.279.1">not</cue> coincide</xcope>, the iORF was discarded.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.280">Similarly, iORFs were compared with RNA genes using BLASTN, and those matched with the RNAs were removed.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.281">Remaining iORFs were translated into amino acid sequences.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.282">We translated all three types of nonsense codons into the one-letter code U, so as to simplify visual inspection of sequence alignments.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.283">Although the code U is usually for selenocysteine, it will be harmless because U is automatically converted into &#215; inside the BLAST programs.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.284">Construction of clusters of conserved iORFs</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.285">To examine evolutionary conservation of the iORFs, a window of 101 residues around the inframe stop codon was extracted and subjected to TBLASTN searches against the above 191 genome sequences.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.286">If there were any hits (E-value &lt; 0.01) in other organisms, and if the hit includes 10 upstream and 10 downstream residues of the inframe stop codon, then the iORF was retained.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.287">However, if there were any hits (E-value &lt; 10-5) that did <xcope id="X1.287.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.287.1">not</cue> cover the inframe stop codon</xcope>, the iORF was discarded.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.288">Eligible iORFs were then clustered using BLASTCLUST with score density 0.5 and minimum length coverage 0.6.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.289">After removing singleton clusters, multiple sequence alignments of the remaining clusters were computed using MAFFT 27 with the L-INS-i option.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.290">Subsequently, conservation of the inframe stop codons in each cluster was examined.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.291">If the location or type of stop codons was <xcope id="X1.291.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.291.1">not</cue> identical</xcope>, the cluster was discarded.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.292">Three-step filtering of the candidate clusters</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.293">The first filter examines protein-likeliness of the iORFs.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.294">This filter is mainly designed to remove conserved non-coding sequences (CNS) immediately downstream of non-readthrough genes.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.295">If we measure purifying selection for amino acid sequences by the ratio of nonsynonymous to synonymous substitution rates (dN/dS), a protein with a stop-codon-encoded amino acid will indicate the sign of selection, while CNS will <xcope id="X1.295.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.295.1">not</cue></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.296">The dN/dS was calculated for each of the two parts flanking the inframe stop codon in an iORF using codeml program in the PAML package 28.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.297">Statistical significance was estimated by likelihood ratio test 29.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.298">The observed alignment was fitted to two distinct substitution models, one of which estimates dN/dS from the data, and the other fixes it to 1.0.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.299">Let lfree and lfix denote log likelihood of these models.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.300">Then, 2&#916;l = 2(lfree &#8211; lfix) approximately follows the &#967;2 distribution with one degree of freedom.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.301">If dN/dS was less than 1.0, and the statistics 2&#916;l was larger than a threshold, we regard it as a sign of purifying selection.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.302">In this study, the threshold was set to 5.0 (corresponds to P &lt; 0.025) so that the known readthrough proteins score higher than the threshold.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.303">For each of the above clusters, an all-against-all comparison of cluster members was performed.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.304">If any pair exhibits such signals in both the N- and C-terminal parts, the cluster was retained.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.305">Even if both the upstream and downstream regions of the inframe stop codon code proteins, they <xcope id="X1.305.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.305.2">may</cue> be two adjacent genes <xcope id="X1.305.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.305.1">instead of</cue> a readthrough protein</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.306">The second and third filtering processes remove such genes based on BLAST alignment patterns.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.307">Although the boundary analysis applied previously has the same goal (Figure 1b), some gene pairs escaped elimination.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.308">To enhance sensitivity of the filters, the whole length of an iORF was used as a BLAST query <xcope id="X1.308.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.308.1">instead of</cue> the partial sequence</xcope>, and the size of the BLAST database was increased from the 191 nonredundant genomes to the 328 complete genomes in GenomeNet and 246 draft genome sequences downloaded from GenBank in May 2006.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.309">The second filter inspects synteny of iORFs.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.310">If the N- and C-terminal parts of an iORF have distinct but closely arranged BLAST hits in other genomes, it strongly <xcope id="X1.310.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.310.1">suggests</cue> the iORF is actually two adjacent genes</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.311">Translated sequences of iORFs in the pre-filtering clusters were subjected to TBLASTN searches against the genome database.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.312">If both the best hits of the N- and C-terminal parts are statistically significant (E-value &lt; 10-5), and distance between them is less than 1 kbp, we call these hits 'syntenic hits'.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.313">If any syntenic hits with non-coinciding reading frames were found, the cluster was removed.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.314">The third filter uses co-occurrence of residues around the inframe stop codon as another source of information for screening stop codon readthrough.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.315">Suppose a window of 21 residues centered at the inframe stop codon.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.316">In prokaryotes, most stop-codon-encoded amino acids are located inside a domain, the unit of evolutionary sequence conservation.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.317">Therefore, in an ideal situation the presence or <xcope id="X1.317.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.317.1">absence</cue> of the 21 residues in alignments</xcope> will be synchronized.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.318">In contrast, if the iORF is actually two adjacent genes, then upstream and downstream residues of the stop codon will appear separately in many alignments.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.319">We defined a co-occurrence matrix as a 21 &#215; 21 matrix whose (i,j)-th element represents how often residue i and j appeared simultaneously in N alignments.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.320">The matrix elements were subsequently normalized to the number of alignments N.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.321">By definition, the more often the upstream and downstream residues of the inframe stop codon co-occur in the alignments, the higher the density in the upper right quarter of the matrix.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.322">If average density in the quarter was lower than 0.85, the cluster was filtered out.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.323">Stop codon usage</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.324">For each organism, its iORFs were extracted from the pre-filtering clusters, and codon usage at the inframe stop positions was counted.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.325">Codon usage at the C-terminal stop codons in its proteome was also computed using data of coding sequences downloaded from KEGG GENES 25.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.326">These data were combined into a 3 &#215; 2 matrix, and Fisher's exact test was applied.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.327">The p-value was corrected for multiple testing using the Bonferroni correction because there were 127 organisms in the pre-filtering clusters.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
		</Document>
