		<Document type="Biological_full_article">
			<DocID type="PMCID">PMC138857</DocID>
				<DocumentPart type="Title">
					<sentence id="S8.1">A comparison of programmed cell death between species</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S8.2">Abstract</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S8.3">Key components of the programmed cell death pathway are conserved between Caenorhabditis elegans, Drosophila melanogaster and humans.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.4">The search for additional homologs has been facilitated by the availability of the entire genomic sequence for each of these organisms.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.5">Programmed cell death is a conserved, gene-directed mechanism for the elimination of unnecessary or dangerous cells from an organism.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.6">The core cell death pathway was first defined through genetic analysis in the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans and has since been found to be conserved in species as diverse as Drosophila melanogaster and Homo sapiens.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.7">The rapid progress of the various genome sequencing projects has greatly accelerated the discovery of homologs for key components of the cell death pathway as well as for its regulators.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.8">The C. elegans genome sequence was completed two years ago [1], and both the Drosophila [2] and human genomes are essentially completely sequenced at this point.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.9">Although many components of the programmed cell death pathway are conserved between species, there are some important differences as well.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S8.10">The core cell death pathway</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S8.11">Programmed cell death has long been known to be a part of normal development, but it was not until the discovery of the first genes essential for the phenomenon that our understanding of the events leading up to the deliberate elimination of a cell began to take shape.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.12">Before this time, programmed cell death was defined by a set of specific morphological characteristics, including chromatin condensation, nuclear shrinkage and blebbing of the plasma membrane that could be observed in dying cells; the term apoptosis was coined to distinguish this type of cell death from necrotic deaths resulting from injury [3,4].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.13">Four genes make up the core programmed cell death pathway in C. elegans, three of which, egl-1 (egg laying abnormal), ced-3 (cell death abnormal), and ced-4, are pro-apoptotic and one, ced-9, is anti-apoptotic (reviewed in [5]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.14">There was considerable excitement in the field when potential mammalian and Drosophila homologs for ced-3, ced-4, ced-9, and egl-1 were discovered.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.15">The CED-3 protein is one of a continuously growing family of specific cysteine proteases, termed caspases, <xcope id="X8.15.1">that are <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.15.1">thought</cue> to be the executioners of programmed cell death</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.16">At least fourteen mammalian caspases have been identified, and they are grouped into two classes on the basis of their proteolytic specificities (reviewed in [6]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.17">Class 1 caspases are mainly involved in cytokine maturation, while Class 2 caspases act mainly in apoptosis.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.18">Class 2 has been further subdivided into two groups: upstream or initiator caspases (group 1), and downstream or effector caspases (group 2).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.19"><xcope id="X8.19.1">Initiator caspases are <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.19.1">thought</cue> to be at the beginning of a proteolytic cascade that amplifies the cell death signal and results in the activation of the effector caspases</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.20">Initiator caspases usually have long pro-domains, while effector caspases have short pro-domains.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.21">Drosophila has at least eight caspases, five of which have been at least partially characterized (Dcp-1, Dcp-2/Dredd, drICE, Dronc, and Decay) and three uncharacterized ones found encoded in the genome sequence [7].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.22"><xcope id="X8.22.1">C. elegans <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.22.1">appears</cue> to have only a single caspase - CED-3 - that is essential for all developmental cell death</xcope>, despite having three other caspases in its genome [8,9].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.23">Three Drosophila caspases - Dcp-2/Dredd, Dronc, and one known only as a sequence in the genome database - have long pro-domains and are thus <xcope id="X8.23.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.23.2">likely</cue> initiator caspases</xcope>; another four - Dcp-1, drICE, Decay, and another one found in the genome database - have short pro-domains and are <xcope id="X8.23.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.23.1">probably</cue> effector caspases</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.24">In addition, Dcp-1 has a substrate specificity that is very similar to that of two effector caspases, mammalian caspase 3 and C. elegans CED-3 [10].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.25">Interestingly, <xcope id="X8.25.1">Dronc <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.25.1">appears</cue> to have a substrate specificity that is so far unique among caspases</xcope>: while all other known caspases have only been shown to cleave after aspartate residues, Dronc can also cleave after glutamate residues [11].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.26">This unusual substrate specificity <xcope id="X8.26.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.26.1">may</cue> explain why Dronc is resistant to inhibition by the pan-caspase inhibitor p35</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.27">On the basis of current data, it <xcope id="X8.27.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.27.1">seems</cue> that CED-4 functions to help activate the caspase CED-3, and CED-9 blocks this activation through physical interaction with CED-4</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.28">Endogenous CED-4 is normally localized to the mitochondria by CED-9, unless EGL-1 is expressed [12,13].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.29">If EGL-1 is expressed, the interaction between CED-4 and CED-9 ceases, and CED-4 translocates to the nuclear membrane where it activates CED-3, resulting in programmed cell death.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.30">Only one mammalian CED-4 homolog, Apaf-1, has been extensively characterized to date, but it too aids in caspase activation.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.31">Like CED-4, Apaf-1 requires dATP for caspase activation, but Apaf-1 requires cytochrome c in addition [14].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.32">Knock-out studies have shown that mice deficient for Apaf-1 have reduced cell death in certain tissues, further <xcope id="X8.32.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.32.1">supporting</cue> a role for Apaf-1 in programmed cell death</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.33">Drosophila has recently been shown also to have a CED-4/Apaf-1 homolog, named Dark/HAC-1/Dapaf-1 (reviewed in [15]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.34">The Drosophila homolog is more similar to Apaf-1 than to CED-4: it has the WD repeats found in Apaf-1, which <xcope id="X8.34.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.34.1">potentially</cue> function in binding regulatory proteins such as cytochrome c</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.35">Like Apaf-1 and CED-4, loss of function mutations in dark/hac-1/dapaf-1 result in a reduction in developmental programmed cell death.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.36">Intriguingly, the transcription of the Drosophila CED-4/Apaf-1 homolog is upregulated in response to both X-ray and ultraviolet irradiation, <xcope id="X8.36.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.36.2">suggesting</cue> that death-inducing stimuli <xcope id="X8.36.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.36.1">can</cue> feed into the cell death pathway at this step</xcope></xcope> [16].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.37">CED-9 and EGL-1 belong to a large family of proteins related to the mammalian anti-apoptotic protein Bcl-2.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.38">This family - with at least 19 members, divided into pro- and anti-apoptotic subgroups - has been largely defined by protein-protein interactions among its members (reviewed in [17]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.39">CED-9 has mammalian counterparts in the anti-apoptotic subgroup of Bcl-2 family members, while EGL-1 has mammalian counterparts in the pro-apoptotic subgroup.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.40">Besides binding to Apaf-1, just as CED-9 binds and thereby regulates CED-4 activity, <xcope id="X8.40.1">mammalian Bcl-2 family members have been <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.40.1">proposed</cue> to regulate mitochondrial homeostasis and the release of pro-apoptotic factors such as cytochrome c</xcope> (reviewed in [17]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.41">The rate of mitochondrial release of cytochrome c in mammalian cells undergoing apoptosis was recently measured and found to be rapid [18].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.42">Indeed, most mitochondria released all their cytochrome c within a one minute period in a temperature-independent manner, <xcope id="X8.42.3"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.42.3">suggesting</cue> that an enzymatic transport mechanism is <xcope id="X8.42.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.42.2">probably</cue> <xcope id="X8.42.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.42.1">not</cue> involved</xcope></xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.43">There is <xcope id="X8.43.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.43.1">no clear evidence</cue> for cytochrome c release during apoptosis in C. elegans or Drosophila, however</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.44">Nevertheless, a specific epitope is uncovered on cytochrome c in Drosophila mitochondria during apoptosis and this <xcope id="X8.44.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.44.1">may</cue> be sufficient to help activate Dark/HAC-1/Dapaf-1</xcope>; and death-inducing stimuli result in an increase in cytochrome c in Drosophila cultured-cell lysates [19,20].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.45">There is <xcope id="X8.45.2"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.45.2">no</cue> apparent need for cytochrome c release in C. elegans</xcope>, since CED-4 does <xcope id="X8.45.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.45.1">not</cue> require it to activate CED-3</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.46">Recently, a pro-apoptotic Drosophila Bcl-2 family member was identified with the help of the database of genomic sequence; this gene is most closely related to mammalian Bok and <xcope id="X8.46.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.46.1">potentially</cue> regulates apoptosis in the fly</xcope> [21,22,23,24].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.47">The Drosophila Bok homolog interacts with several anti-apoptotic, but <xcope id="X8.47.2"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.47.2">not</cue> with several pro-apoptotic, Bcl-2 family members</xcope> and, therefore, <xcope id="X8.47.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.47.1">possibly</cue> functions by antagonizing pro-survival proteins</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.48">Ectopic expression of Bok protein promotes apoptosis in transgenic flies as well as in cultured cells.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.49">While one group reports that the caspase inhibitor p35 can block apoptosis induced by Drosophila Bok [22], another group did <xcope id="X8.49.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.49.1">not</cue> see p35 inhibition</xcope> [23].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.50">This difference <xcope id="X8.50.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.50.1">may</cue> be due to the slightly different constructs used in the experiments and the different assay systems</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.51">A third group shows that peptide caspase inhibitors can block Drosophila Bok-mediated apoptosis in cell culture, lending support to a model in which expression of Bok protein leads to caspase activation [24].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.52">Interestingly, ectopic expression of Drosophila Bok sensitizes the developing eye to cell death induced by ultraviolet irradiation [21].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.53">Genetically, <xcope id="X8.53.3">this Drosophila Bcl-2 family member <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.53.3">appears</cue> to function <xcope id="X8.53.2">upstream of, <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.53.2">or</cue> in parallel to</xcope>, the Drosophila ced-4/apaf-1 homolog and <xcope id="X8.53.1">downstream of, <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.53.1">or</cue> in parallel to</xcope>, the Drosophila regulators of apoptosis, reaper, hid, and grim</xcope> [22].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.54">The core components of the cell death pathway are illustrated in Figure 1.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="FigureLegend">
					<sentence id="S8.55">The core pathway of programmed cell death.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S8.56">Multiple pathways lead to the activation of the executioners of death, the caspases (reviewed in [53]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.57">IAPs (inhibitors of apoptosis) have been shown to block the conversion of pro-caspases into active enzymes, and Reaper, Hid, Grim, and Diablo/Smac prevent IAPs from carrying out this protective function.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.58">Caspases can also be activated with the aid of Apaf-1, <xcope id="X8.58.1">which in turn <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.58.1">appears</cue> to be regulated by cytochrome c and dATP</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.59">The <xcope id="X8.59.2">Bcl-2 family <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.59.2">appears</cue> to function in regulating the release of pro-apoptotic components from mitochondria as well as by <xcope id="X8.59.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.59.1">possibly</cue> inhibiting Apaf-1 directly</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.60">This pathway integrates knowledge gained in multiple species, showing that <xcope id="X8.60.1">apoptosis <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.60.1">appears</cue> to be regulated in a similar manner regardless of the organism</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.61">One notable exception is that <xcope id="X8.61.1"><xcope id="X8.61.2">the C.elegans homologs of IAPs do <cue type="negation" ref="X8.61.1">not</cue> <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.61.2">appear</cue> to function in programmed cell death</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S8.62">Regulation of programmed cell death</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S8.63">Studies of Drosophila have yielded great insights into how programmed cell death is regulated (reviewed in [25]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.64">In addition to the core pathway, several essential regulators have been characterized in Drosophila.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.65">A region in the genome which contains the genes reaper, head involution defective (hid), and grim has been shown to be essential for virtually all developmental cell death in the Drosophila embryo.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.66">The three proteins encoded by these genes have no significant homology to any other known proteins except for a small stretch of similarity at the amino terminus that is shared by all three but <xcope id="X8.66.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.66.1">no</cue> other known proteins</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.67">Each of these three genes can induce programmed cell death when overexpressed in the developing Drosophila eye or in various tissue-culture assays.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.68">In addition, Reaper, Hid and Grim are able to induce apoptosis in heterologous systems, <xcope id="X8.68.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.68.1">suggesting</cue> that vertebrate homologs of these proteins exist</xcope> (reviewed in [26]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.69">Further evidence for the existence of vertebrate homologs of Reaper, Hid, and Grim come from observations that these three proteins are able to bind a class of inhibitors of apoptosis, or IAPs.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.70">IAPs were first discovered in baculovirus, but have since been shown to play a vital role in blocking apoptosis in Drosophila as well as in mammals (reviewed in [27]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.71">Also, Hid has been shown to be negatively regulated by survival signals mediated by receptor tyrosine kinases through the Ras and mitogen-activated protein (MAP) kinase pathway, which is also well conserved in mammals [28,29].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.72">More recently, reports of a <xcope id="X8.72.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.72.1">potential</cue> functional mammalian analog of Reaper, Hid, and Grim</xcope> have been published [30,31].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.73">Although Diablo/Smac shares <xcope id="X8.73.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.73.1">no</cue> sequence homology with Reaper, Hid, or Grim</xcope>, it too can bind IAPs, preventing them from inhibiting caspase activation, and thereby inducing apoptosis.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.74">Furthermore, Diablo/Smac interacts through its amino terminus with the BIR (baculovirus IAP repeat) domains of IAPs, similar to Reaper, Hid, and Grim [32,33].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.75">An important difference between the function of Diablo/Smac and Reaper, Hid, and Grim is that Diablo/Smac is <xcope id="X8.75.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.75.1">not</cue> pro-apoptotic by itself when overexpressed</xcope>, but instead requires a death-inducing stimulus to promote apoptosis, unlike the three Drosophila proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.76">Table 1 provides a summary of the conserved regulators of cell death across species.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.77">In contrast to cell death effectors such as caspases, the cell death regulators Reaper and Grim are specifically expressed several hours before apoptosis in cells destined to die (reviewed in [26]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.78">The expression of reaper has been shown to be regulated by distinct stimuli, including X-irradiation, steroid hormone signaling and a block in cell differentiation ([34,35,36] and A.-F. Lambin and H.S., unpublished observations).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.79">Recently, a Drosophila p53 ortholog was identified by searching the genome database (reviewed in [37]), and it was shown to bind a specific region of the reaper promoter, thereby <xcope id="X8.79.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.79.1">potentially</cue> regulating reaper transcription in response to ionizing radiation</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.80">Furthermore, the reaper promoter was also shown to contain a response element for the complex made up of the steroid hormone ecdysone and its receptor [36].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.81">The observation that transcription of both reaper and dark/hac-1/dapaf-1 can be induced by ionizing radiation <xcope id="X8.81.2"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.81.2">suggests</cue> that these death-inducing signals <xcope id="X8.81.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.81.1">can</cue> feed into the cell death pathway at multiple points</xcope></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.82">Unlike reaper and grim, <xcope id="X8.82.1">hid <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.82.1">appears</cue> to be regulated not only transcriptionally but also post-translationally by the Ras-MAP kinase pathway</xcope> [28,29].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.83">This additional level of control for hid <xcope id="X8.83.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.83.1">could</cue> explain the observation that hid is expressed in cells that are doomed to die as well as in cells that continue to survive</xcope> [38].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.84">A second class of key apoptotic regulators in Drosophila is the IAP family.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.85">IAPs contain at least one, and up to three, BIR domains, which are important for protein-protein interactions, and often a carboxy-terminal RING domain (reviewed in [27]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.86">While several IAPs have been implicated in inhibiting apoptosis, proteins with single BIR domains can also have functions in cell cycle regulation and cytokinesis [39,40].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.87">In fact, Saccharomyces cerevisiae contains <xcope id="X8.87.2"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.87.2">neither</cue> caspases <cue type="negation" ref="X8.87.2">nor</cue> an apoptotic program</xcope>, but it does have an IAP-like protein with a single BIR domain that functions in regulating cell division [41], <xcope id="X8.87.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.87.1">suggesting</cue> that the IAPs are diverse family with only some members being anti-apoptotic</xcope>: hence this protein family is more accurately referred to as BIR-containing proteins (BIRPs).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.88">Three Drosophila BIRPs have been shown to be inhibitors of apoptosis, Diap1, Diap2, and Deterin [42,43,44,45].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.89">Of these, Diap1 has been most extensively characterized; it can block cell death caused by the ectopic expression of reaper, hid, and grim (reviewed in [26]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.90">In addition, Diap1 is able to block the cell death induced by the Drosophila caspases Dcp-1 or drICE in Saccharomyces, as well as apoptosis induced by the expression of drICE in insect cell culture [46,47,48].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.91">Loss-of-function mutants in diap1 have a very striking early embryonic phenotype: virtually all cells display an apoptotic morphology, as well as displaying DNA fragmentation seen by TUNEL labeling, four to five hours into development [47,49,50].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.92">This phenotype is especially noteworthy since it manifests itself several hours before the first developmental cell deaths are normally observed in the Drosophila embryo, and it clearly shows that diap1 is vital for normal development.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.93">In general, <xcope id="X8.93.1">IAPs are <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.93.1">thought</cue> to function at the caspase activation step in the cell death pathway, binding to the inactive, pro-domain-containing caspase zymogen and preventing it from being processed into the active enzyme</xcope> (reviewed in [27]).</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.94">Reaper, Hid, Grim, and Diablo/Smac can physically interact with IAPs, thereby inhibiting the anti-apoptotic activity of IAPs and allowing caspase activation.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.95">Further insight into a <xcope id="X8.95.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.95.1">possible</cue> mechanism for IAP function</xcope> was recently gained when IAPs were observed to have ubiquitin ligase activity [51,52].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.96">It was shown that certain cellular IAPs can be degraded in a proteasome-dependent manner prior to thymocyte apoptosis.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.97">These IAPs are also capable of auto-ubiquitination, an activity shown to require the RING domain [52].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.98">In addition, IAPs can mono-ubiquitinate several caspases in vitro, <xcope id="X8.98.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.98.1">possibly</cue> marking them for degradation</xcope>, and again, this activity requires the RING domain [51].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.99"><xcope id="X8.99.1">The exact role of the ubiquitination pathway in regulating apoptosis is still <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.99.1">unclear</cue></xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.100">Even the role of the RING domain in IAPs is open to debate: mutations in the RING domain of endogenous diap1 <xcope id="X8.100.3"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.100.3">can</cue> be <xcope id="X8.100.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X8.100.1">either</cue> pro- <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.100.1">or</cue> anti-apoptotic</xcope></xcope>, depending on the death-inducing stimulus ([49] and J. Agapite, L. Goyal, K. McCall and H.S., unpublished observations).</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="TableLegend">
					<sentence id="S8.101">Conservation of key regulators of programmed cell death between species</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S8.102">Strengths and limitations of genomic analysis</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S8.103">The completed genomes of C. elegans and Drosophila have already yielded a wealth of information.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.104">New cell death gene homologs are being described at a very rapid pace, often by several laboratories at once.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.105">Using information from the genome project, C. elegans was shown to contain several potential caspases in addition to CED-3, but <xcope id="X8.105.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.105.1">none</cue> of these has been shown to function in programmed cell death</xcope> [9].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.106">In addition, while C. elegans has two BIR-domain-containing proteins, <xcope id="X8.106.1"><xcope id="X8.106.2"><cue type="negation" ref="X8.106.1">neither</cue> <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.106.2">appears</cue> to regulate cell death</xcope></xcope>: BIR-1 has been demonstrated to be essential for cytokinesis instead [39].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.107">Hence, <xcope id="X8.107.1">C. elegans <cue type="speculation" ref="X8.107.1">seems</cue> to have a mechanism for regulating caspase activation that differs from that of mammals and Drosophila, in that it relies solely on the two Bcl-2 family members</xcope> [53].</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.108">For Drosophila, the genome project played a key role in the identification of the Bcl-2 family member(s) and the CED-4/Apaf-1 homolog, showing that the core cell death pathway is conserved in Drosophila as well.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.109">Various other homologs for cell death genes, including three additional caspase-like sequences and a second Bcl-2 family member have been identified in the Drosophila genome sequence [7] and will undoubtedly be published in the near future.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.110">And analysis of the human genomic sequence is sure to lead to a better understanding of the number of mammalian homologs for the various components of the cell death pathway.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.111">While it is clear that the search for homologs of known cell death genes has been greatly facilitated by the availability of the entire genome sequence for C. elegans, Drosophila, and humans, there are limitations to this strategy.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.112">For instance, the small size of the Reaper protein - only of 65 amino acids - makes it extremely difficult to identify homologs on the basis of genomic sequence information in other species: current gene-finding programs typically require an open reading frame of at least 70 amino acids.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.113">Furthermore, there is considerable divergence even among cell death proteins with clearly homologous functions, such as CED-4/Apaf-1 and even CED-9/Bcl-2, and sequence homology between these genes was recognized only after the genes and their products had been functionally characterized.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S8.114">Nevertheless, in combination with traditional approaches including genetics and biochemistry, knowledge of the genome sequence for model organisms will undoubtedly continue to drive our rapidly increasing insights into the molecular basis of programmed cell death.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
		</Document>
