		<Document type="Biological_full_article">
			<DocID type="BMC_ID">1471-2105-8-225</DocID>
				<DocumentPart type="Title">
					<sentence id="S1.1">Mining prokaryotic genomes for unknown amino acids: a stop-codon-based approach</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.2">Abstract</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SubSectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.3">Background</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.4">Selenocysteine and pyrrolysine are the 21st and 22nd amino acids, which are genetically encoded by stop codons.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.5">Since a number of microbial genomes have been completely sequenced to date, it is tempting to ask <xcope id="X1.5.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.5.1">whether</cue> the 23rd amino acid is left undiscovered in these genomes</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.6">Recently, a computational study addressed this question and reported that <xcope id="X1.6.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.6.1">no</cue> tRNA gene for unknown amino acid was found in genome sequences available</xcope>.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.7">However, <xcope id="X1.7.2">performance of the tRNA prediction program on an unknown tRNA family, which <xcope id="X1.7.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.7.1">may</cue> have atypical sequence and structure</xcope>, is <cue type="speculation" ref="X1.7.2">unclear</cue></xcope>, thereby rendering their result inconclusive.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.8">A protein-level study will provide independent insight into the novel amino acid.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="SubSectionTitle">
					<sentence id="S1.9">Results</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
				<DocumentPart type="Text">
					<sentence id="S1.10"><xcope id="X1.10.1"><cue type="speculation" ref="X1.10.1">Assuming</cue> that the 23rd amino acid is also encoded by a stop codon</xcope>, we systematically predicted proteins that contain stop-codon-encoded amino acids from 191 prokaryotic genomes.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.11">Since our prediction method relies only on the conservation patterns of primary sequences, it also provides an opportunity to search novel selenoproteins and other readthrough proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.12">It successfully recovered many of currently known selenoproteins and pyrrolysine proteins.</sentence>
					<sentence id="S1.13">However, <xcope id="X1.13.1"><cue type="negation" ref="X1.13.1">no</cue> promising candidate for the 23rd amino acid was detected</xcope>, and only one novel selenoprotein was predicted.</sentence>
				</DocumentPart>
		</Document>
